<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Intro | The Blog of Ryan T. Harter]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.ryantharter.com/blog/categories/intro/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.ryantharter.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-30T12:19:53-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.ryantharter.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ryan T. Harter]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Apple not #1]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ryantharter.com/blog/2012/08/22/apple-not-number-1/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-22T19:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ryantharter.com/blog/2012/08/22/apple-not-number-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I, like most economists, have been amused by the recent bout of headlines claiming Apple is now the most valuable company of all time; in nominal dollars, of course.
This <a href="http://money.cnn.com/2012/08/20/technology/apple-most-valuable-company/">CNN Money article</a>, and comparable articles from many
<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/us-stock-futures-fall-ahead-of-pivotal-week-in-europe-lowes-misses-wall-street-expectations/2012/08/20/a414ce76-eac0-11e1-866f-60a00f604425_story.html">reputable</a>
<a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/carminegallo/2012/08/21/7-courageous-ways-apple-became-americas-most-valuable-company/">news</a>
<a href="http://in.reuters.com/article/2012/08/21/idINL2E8JKC8C20120821">agencies</a>
offer a catchy headline without substance wasting several paragraphs of reader time before admitting that the comparison is worthless.
I'm suprised that with today's focus on fuel efficiency the media missed this whopper of a headline:</p>

<h2>NASA's Curiosity is now the lightest mode of transportation of all time</h2>

<p>On their way to exploring the red planet, NASA set another record: It produced the lightest vehicle in all of history.</p>

<p>Curiosity's weight crept below .01 oz. before landing on the fourth rock from the sun. For comparison, the average racing bike weighs more than 240oz.</p>

<p>...</p>

<p>NASA still has one last hurdle to climb: Curiosity is still heavier than most forms of transportation if changes in the force of gravity are accounted for. On the ground, Curiosity weighed just north of 8,000 pounds</p>

<h2>What's the difference?</h2>

<p>Generally, we can compare the mass of two objects by measuring their weight.
However, this comparison breaks down if we take the measurement at different locations.
As we increase our elevation, gravity's effect on the mass of an object decreases, decreasing the weight.
Therefore the weight of a 4kg bowling ball is different at sea level, at the top of Mt. Everest, and is weightless in space.
A comparison of the weight of the Curiosity Mars rover in space to a bicycle on the ground makes little sense.
Because the objects are far apart, it would be more logical to use a measure that is not affected by distance from the earth.</p>

<p>Similarly, we commonly use dollars as a yardstick to compare value.
One can reasonably argue that of two items the one that has the highest price is the most valuable to the market.
However, this comparison breaks down over time.</p>

<p>For now, let's define the value of a dollar to be total GDP divided by the amount of dollars in the market.
Thus, each dollar is a voucher for ownership of some portion of the goods produced by the country.
If the government were to print a fresh batch of bills overnight the value per dollar, or the share of GDP represented by each dollar, would decrease.
This decision would not change the value of Apple.
However, because the value per dollar has decreased the number of dollars required to purchase apple will increase.
The number of dollars required to purchase something is the nominal cost.
A comparison of the nominal value of Microsoft in 1999 to Apple in 2012 makes little sense.
Because the companies are far apart in time, it would be more logical to use a measure that is not affected by the time of measurement.
Because of this flaw, comparisons of value across time are done in 'real' terms, which are adjusted for the changes in the value per dollar.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
